this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se Radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software radio my name is Sven and
today I'm sitting here with Simon from
and Simon is an independent consultant
and trainer and the creator of the C for
software architecture model he also
wrote a book software architecture for
developers how are you saying I'm very
good thank you very good thanks
anything correct uh no I mean as as you
said I'm an independent consultant my
background is actually in consulting and
building software mostly in London and
mostly in Java for banks so that that's
kind of my software development
background but over the past few years
I've been guessing around and radiating
lots of consulting training and helping
teams understand what software
architecture is and how they can blend
it with lightweight agile ways of
working ok you're proposing sketching is
an effective way of creating and
communicating software architecture so
first of all why communicating software
architecture if you if you look back say
10 20 years we we used to have a very
process heavy document heavy hi ceremony
way of doing design so this is the go
capture all the requirements do all the
design and then document that design and
a big chunky hefty document and then UML
came along and everybody was buying UML
tools and modeling tore them who are
spending months and months and months
just doing design
fast forward to 12 years ago and the
whole a draft thing came along and I
think we've we've gone from one extreme
right back to the other extreme where
yeah lots of teams are basically doing
nothing so what I'm trying to do is I'm
trying to push the needle somewhere back
towards the middle
we had big design up front then no
design up front and right and now you're
trying to forget that just enough yeah
and of course I tell doesn't say don't
do design but it's that's many people's
interpretation of what you know the
agile manifesto and agile approaches
savor that that's not easy no actually
the case
so yeah I'm trying to get people
thinking about design again and I'm
trying to provide a nice lightweight
mechanism that people can use to share
things ideas because after all you have
this fantastic idea for how to how to
for how to build a software system and
the team needs to understand it and
really that's the whole purpose of
sketching okay so the the stakeholders
of the architecture is is the team right
software developers you know we are the
biggest stakeholders of software
architecture so that's the primary
audience who are targeting for example
these sketches okay okay okay
one of the benefits of sketches what are
the benefits of sketches it's it's
really about being able to communicate
and share that vision that we create of
you know this design of this
architecture of the thing we want to
build and the thing about sketching is
that implies a certain degree of
lightweightness if that's a word
and what I'm trying to avoid is is going
into this big model driven up front
design process where we have to think
through lots of things and really this
is about getting the majority of ideas
down quickly in a way that's accessible
to developers okay so it's okay to use
stuff hours it's better to be incomplete
but right yeah so I mean we're
definitely looking for some preciseness
here especially around some of the
higher levels of abstraction but what I
don't want to do for example is drop
down to class level details so if people
if people are skeptical ass diagrams
maybe we have to question why and what
the value of doing that
exactly sketches are not formalized
so there are probably many many ways I
can create a sketch and especially
ineffective it's just so what is the
what is a bad sketch or an ineffective
sketch what is a bad sketch what is an
ineffective sketch uh-huh so that there
are lots and lots of answers they're
part of that the workshop that I do is I
get people to design a solution and draw
some pictures and I don't give them much
guidance at all and I would say probably
upwards of 90% of those sketches are
ineffective they're ineffective for a
number of reasons first of all is the
notational side of things so people
don't tend to use your mouth and you
mail as a standardized formalized
notation but if people are not using UML
then they're essentially event inventing
their own abstractions and notation and
that causes a lot of confusion that as
I'm sure you can imagine and as well as
the notation it's really those
abstractions so we find lots of sketches
with mix abstractions mix levels of
detail where people have drawn multiple
sketches and show different views of the
architecture it's not clear what the
relationship between those different
sketches is for example I can imagine
when I studied my software architecture
professor always made fun of marketing
sure it's not all that even if you go to
the Oracle website and you look at the
architecture of the JDK it's just boxes
with some colors right yeah
nobody nice and gradient changes so it
looks nice you know horrible color
schemes but then you don't know what
what the screen means okay are you
mentioned human and I'm just wondering
is this UML and the tools around you man
are they dead nobody talks about it I
mean sometimes people people even don't
know what you man is that's very trivial
I think there are some universities who
no longer teaching people your mom from
from my perspective I I do still use
humor but I use it very very sparingly
and I use a very small number of you
Mart diagrams for a very specific
reasons though class diagrams for
showing classes and how they interact
I like activity diagrams to show
workflows and that comfits state charts
mistakes and sequence of collaboration
diagrams if you want to show
interactions between things with that's
pretty much it I don't use your mouth
for the kind of quote/unquote
architecture diagrams and I don't see
many people using UML talking anymore
one of the one of the questions I
regularly ask my my audiences at talks
and workshops is now how many people
here use UML and I've asked this
question in the United States and half
of Europe and China and Australia and
Dubai and it's about one out of ten
people okay I've recently had a bunch of
audience where it's been zero oh sorry
so is UML dead I think the numbers
probably point to it being dead okay so
it is pressing - yeah I mean at least
it's a lot of ideas are not dead but
it's probably just a notation and where
people just don't wanna dive into yeah
it's it's just too complex if it I mean
because it grows you so much yeah I mean
how many diagram topsolid 20 or
something ion's he could tell you I lost
sight after one point four I think after
that it was just too much yeah
the the best UML book I've ever read was
martin fowler's I think if UML 1.12
still which is what like 15 years ago
something and that was the best book on
that whole topic okay okay let's go to
the C form or the first I just want you
mentioned vitamins mantra so who is ben
shneiderman and what is his mother
that's very good question so I don't
actually know who he is but his mantra
is basically well it's a way to deal
with lots and lots of data and this has
recently introduced to me by bonnie
other speakers at a conference i
attended
and essentially if you have a huge
amount of stuff to deal with what you
want to do first is get an overview then
you want to zoom and filter so you're
kind of dropping down into a subset of
the dataset and then if you want more
information you can get that on demand
so what does it got to do anything so
that the c4 model is basically a way of
very very simply describing the software
system and in order to understand see
morph c4 model you need to kind of
backtrack slightly and say why how do
you represent and think about a software
system so a software system for me is
made up of a number of containers these
are basically deployable or executing
executable units something that you can
host code or data in those containers
contain components what's a component
it's just a bunch of stuff related Hokie
he Civ with a nice clean interface
because I deal with Java and.net and my
components made of classes and then once
you understand that simple tree
structure so system containers
components classes you can then draw a
diagram at each level intent so start
with the system context picture which
basically says here's my system in the
middle and around it are my different
types of users and system dependencies
you then open up the system to show the
containers inside it you then open up
each interesting container to show the
components and then optionally you can
open up the component show the classes
so the sea falls are context containers
component classes so to come back to
Snyderman s'matter
the overview first I'd consider to be
the context and contains pictures
because that gives you a nice starting
point a zoomin filter is come zooming
into one container and looking at the
components inside it and then
details-on-demand for me is the class
diagrams okay and the sort of context
diagram it shows users the system and
the system it's quite it's quite a
rating yes yeah exactly so it's normally
very simply the system you're working on
your key different types of users you
can call them actors or wrote roles or
personas attempt to you and then yeah as
you said it's your key system
collaborations so everything from
systems you send data to system
you get dates from your Active Directory
survey email server your monitoring
system all of those sorts of things and
it's they call this their diagram
stakeholders basically everybody so
everybody from you know people paying
business people through to Isis
developers so we can get a starting
point for why we've got a new system and
really have fits into the rest of our
varmint typical people operations
support maintenance you know there's
basic that diagrams useful for everybody
it's just a really nice simple starting
point okay then the container when I do
container these days I always think
about TACA TACA yes this is I'm gonna
show you document now say what you mean
with the contain the the simple answer
is possibly so if let's imagine that you
are building a system and it's made up
of a web server talking to a database
how would you deploy that in terms of
docker containers we might have a docker
container for the database a bunch of
docker containers for your webserver so
in that sense it kind of matches up so
what I mean by container is is something
that can host code or data essentially
it's a separately deployable thing so
web server application server windows
service loan application browser mobile
client any of those sorts of things okay
and then it also contains the diagram
contains technology choices or yeah so
might might support contain so grab this
is kind of hard to show on a podcast
without without visuals but if you take
the context diagram basically you'll
just zooming into your system and it
really just shows you know the
interaction between let's say your
mobile app talking to your website
talking to a database I'm just storing
stuff in the filesystem whatever it is
that your systems by now it's only
showing logical containers so okay
imagine I'm storing data in my sequel
database and it's actually a costs or a
deployment time I don't want to show a
whole plus reserves I'm just showing you
know
logical myself don't be okay and yeah it
has Tetris on so you know if it's my
super day space I'm going to say this is
my okay oh and the Bob said the web is
an implementation detail and not part of
the architecture why should I then
include technology choices the web is an
implementation detail I only get where
he's coming from here so let's let's
answer the other question first because
it's simpler why should I show
technology choices on my containers
picture because ultimately I have to
build and deploy and support this thing
at some point if we're building a let's
say we're going to build this web app
and we need to solve a somewhat we are
going to have to choose a database we're
going to have to choose a website we're
going to have to choose a programming
language so there are some choices that
we we must make up front and one
containers picture if I'm doing if I'm
drawing in containers picture as part of
my upfront design exercise may be the
technology choice has not been decided
so maybe we just list out options but if
we're drawing a containers diagram
retrospectively to describe an existing
system then there's no reason not to put
the Tetris or something so the reason
two major reason why I like putting
Tetris on architecture pictures is that
it brings the architecture pictures back
down to earth again I'm sure you've seen
the sous-chef when you flick through
documentation in large organizations and
they have all these nice fluffy Market
Ector pictures and it's just you know
nebulous terms is just conceptual blobs
kind of floating around talking to
another once you start to protect her
wishes on you know from my perspective
as a developer I can start to really see
and visualize and understand how that
thing works in the real world they
probably need some for me it's important
there some traceability between fluffy
diagrams or there let's say from
diagrams to code and if if it's just too
high level then and on and then it's
really hard to trace it but yeah so the
first are going to need to have some
some values needs yeah in the
stakeholders of the container
stakeholders are
the container diagram are definitely us
as developers because that allows us to
kind of step back from you know a
feature we're building and look at the
entire system and how it hangs together
and also operations and support staff by
which I mean people who are not
necessarily developers but who are going
to be running an operating and
maintaining your system and often those
those people have a technical background
because you know the Dean way of
structure and provisioning services and
they do want to know some technical
knowledge but they don't necessarily
want to know how your code is structured
mmm so they want to know there's a
website a talking-to database with a
firewall in between but there that
really care what's inside your website
but operations people probably care we
do have only one instance of this thingy
or n licenses oh dude do you add that
also then to the diagram that you at
least say oh yeah this is can have one
or many so normally no I try to leave my
containers diagram just showing the
logical static structure and I'll have a
separate diagram which talks about how
we map that into infrastructure so this
is where we have you know you have one
swap server and it's to pull it across
this farm of ten servers and this
database cluster okay but it's not part
of the see for the night it's C for plus
plus oh yeah as you come back okay so
first maybe go we can go to the
components so what is a component in NC
4 I've adopted the simplest meaning of
component I think I possibly could it
basically it's a bunch of related stuff
with it a nice clean interface on top
now I don't really want to get involved
in discussions around how people
decompose their systems of hands come up
with a list of components that's that's
entirely up to you know the design
process and and the preferences that
they have so all I mean by component is
a bunch of later stuff a nice clean
interest so for example this could be
something like a loking component which
could wrap up and dr. Jekyll's logging
we could call that
I don't quite know it has a task it has
a set responsibilities and I can create
a nice clean interface on top one of the
things I talk about in my book is it's a
simple financial risk system I have a
bunch requirements of that so if if we
were doing component level design for
the risk system maybe you'd have like a
risk calculator component which does all
the heavy lifting the calculations maybe
there are some data import components
maybe there's a data motor component
maybe there's a an alerting monitoring
component so it's that kind of
granularity of stuff okay and how do I
know is it only a drawing or do you also
have been text because from another
method I know what every component you
just say oh this component needs as
inputs something from other components
and it exposes this and that yeah so if
you look at if you look at UML you must
have a component diagram and there are a
couple of very notations one's got the
two boxes sticking out one side of the
box and one's got the cup and ball
notation for interfacing and continuing
the interface depending on the interface
I flynn's people struggle with that
notation so I keep the notation very
simple line and on the component diagram
each component is just a box there's a
component name
there's optionally a description of the
technology choice again if it's you know
being implemented already we can fillet
and I draft a list of responsibilities
just to give a flavor of what that
component is do and there are a number
of reasons for adding responsibilities
in the diagram but but firstly and I
guess more and more fundamentally it
allows you to have a quick at a glance
view at a diagram and see how your
responsibilities are carved up across
your components in terms of the the
relationships I just draw them as single
single line single arrows and I normally
show
dependency or using a style relationship
so if component ain't dependence on
component B I'll draw a line from A to B
with an arrow pointing towards B and a
little annotation on the line saying
depends on all users age from in the
depends on business since we have no
notation everybody comes up with the own
notation it's important to say this is
not just right yeah so and so if you
look at my arrows on my diagrams they're
they're pretty much all you need
direction so I point one way and they're
all annotated on the line
so hopefully the direction of the arrow
and the annotation match up to explain
what their relationships if I now zoom
into my container and as all my
components in the container I probably
have redundancy because there are some
shared components shared components
between containers yeah so that these
ones I have to draw basically he'll
double and point so mark then it's used
as we know order yeah so let's say that
we we're building a system and let's say
that there's a web application serving
users and let's say there's an API
server which is serving automated client
and let's say that there's a shared
audit or logging component that's used
with it both you know same same code
basic technology so yeah and so I would
draw both of those say audit logging
components in both boxes and just maybe
annotate to say actually this is coming
from a shared library that we're in
control okay
so again just just adding hints to the
diagram to to portray more information
if needed but
if I could draw all these diagrams I can
imagine what I do it then and I shared
libraries and then I think ah now I
understand it much better and I was
wrong in all my diagrams or in a lot of
diagrams and then what do i do then
because for me I do after the sketch I
make a photo right and then after we
throw all of them again yes so this is
where we transition from sketches to
something a bit more formalized and
historically we've done this pipe by
opening our video or PowerPoint and kind
of looking at the sketches we have on
the walls and drawing boxes in
PowerPoint in Visio to match and that's
that's not sure I've been on that a lot
in the past but what I'm trying to do
now is I'm trying to come up with a way
where we can create software after two
models of code so you'll notice I'm
using the word model there the the sea
floor diagrams are based upon an
underlying model so this is the system
contains components classes so what I'm
trying to do is is provide a way so
people can write simple code to
reconstruct that model and then we can
visualize it so so essentially if you go
onto my website cutting the architecture
there are a bunch of blog posts about it
it's it's called structure Iser
so essentially there's a there's a java
implementation sitting on github at the
moment and it's a bunch of java classes
so there's there's java implementation
and there are a bunch of java classes
and those java classes represent things
like systems containers components and
the relationships between those things
and basically what you do is you write a
short a little bit of Java code to say
right I'm going to model my my system so
you do software system x equals new
software system person y equals in
person person why don't you use a system
X and you kind of build up the the
underlying model behind the diagram oh
okay okay okay now I got it right in the
beginning I thought because I've seen
that before that you
and all patients for instance and then
you have a reengineering tool and there
are engineering tool is trying to
abstract everything but what you're
saying is you basically program your
model and program your model with
character yeah so 120 credit model then
there are a bunch of other classes one
is called a system context view of ones
go to containers for you want to put the
pointer view and then you can create
those things you can you can put bits of
the model into the view and then and
then that's essentially a programmatic
representation of the diagrams that you
draw so that that's that's a half the
story so that allows you to build them
all up you still need to visualize it
and that's why I'm building a
diagramming tool which lets you models
so so coming back to your other question
back essentially you know you you create
a sketch you start where Isis from
carrying realize your sketches wrong
because you've got some feedback and
you've learned some stuff how do you
keep the diagrams up-to-date so what I'm
also trying to do is is add in some code
that will automatically extract in this
case component out of your code base and
allowing you to automatically populate
that object model using your code base
okay okay before I come back to this
yeah the was the the programming the
model was that influenced by by
architecture 80s architectural
definition languages is it something
like this I don't know what an 80-year
it's I say only member named
architecture description languages I
I've never really seen these used in the
wild I've read bits about them mostly in
kind of academic circles but I've never
ever really seen people use them so in
answer to your question was these
software architectures code implements
by ADL's the answer's no I'll be
brutally honest and tell you where the
idea came from so this diagram tool I'm
creating I wanted to build a really
simple diagramming tool where as a user
all you need to do is drag boxes around
in order to do that he needed the
underlying model and and did this thing
called structure either start out
that's basically a web application where
you would fire up and you would get a
whole bunch of HTML forms where you
could enter all the names of your
systems and to all the names of your
actors into all the names of your
containers into all names each of your
components plug them all together and
then it would draw diagrams and it
sucked out that the user experience was
just awful because even for a small
system you had to go through all these
HTML forms and pages to basically plug
all the DayTripper behind the scenes of
that web application was this domain
model so there is a domain world
representing systems and contains an
opponent and when I was playing around a
thing as writing some tests for that
domain model I thought actually this is
a much better way to to describe a
software architecture but just by just
by using a domain model I'm wiring
classes together
so I pulled it out of the web app and
that's basically what structure Iser is
okay in the reverse engineering part is
that also something from what structure
Iser office yes yeah so this is a part
of the open source library and if you
look at what traditional diagramming
tools do and static analysis tools what
they do is you put them on your code
base and they say right I've analyzed
your code base for you here's a list of
all your packages and all the
dependencies between the packages and
then you kind of don't click package and
it shows you all the classes inside the
package oh I didn't want to do that
because there's there are many many
types of classes in typical software
system I really don't care about format
from an architecture perspective so what
I'm trying to do is I'm trying to only
extract the architecture II significant
building blocks in other words the
components from the code base so the
question becomes how do you identify
things that are significant versus those
are not and it's entirely up to you this
is your data but what I normally find is
if you look at a typical Enterprise Java
code base people will name things using
a naming convention sometimes
unconsciously so you'll see your scan
through say a java enterprise system and
a bunch of the classes where we will be
named something service or something
module or something
so Lina let's use naming conventions to
extract elements from the codebase and
call those our quote unquote components
if you're using something like spring
MVC
so we're spring MVC you use the spring
annotations to annotate you know this is
a web controller this is a service this
is a repository great - let's use those
concepts and call those out components
and we'll extract those and put them
into the model okay so there are almost
different strategies depending on the
system you're building and the languages
that you use it's that kind of concept
so rather than pulling out all of the
utils or the domain classes and all the
implementations of your window Kappa
okay okay cross-cutting concerns like
security or scalability how do we
remember those two sketches the simple
answer is if you don't and so that the
sketches I focus on are just around the
static structure and are normally having
the smaller sketches or more often some
texts to describe how how would your
security how it is scaling or locking
that sort of thing so across cutting
concerns it might be don't feel very
well diagrams C 4 so we have context
containers component classes that's all
static description of software
architecture but I might be interested
in dynamic behavior is that then part of
some press press yeah so it's C 4 plus 4
so so as you said C 4 is just the static
structure and that goes from classes
through components containers and up to
the system once you and understand the
static structure of the thing you have
either you want to how well all you've
built you can then show collaboration
diagrams or sequence diagrams that show
the interaction between components for
example to satisfy our feature or use
because a user story so that's what I'd
rather do I'd rather focus on getting
the static structure understood and then
use other techniques to to supplement
the static model with collaborations
runtime behavioral diagrams and that's
what basically the major use cases are
then more than an activity
diagram yeah yeah yeah into T diagram
collaboration tournaments having any
other I've been you said the deployments
yeah so so are other diagrams that may
or may not be useful to describe your
software system everything from
wireframes and UI mock-ups through to
models of the business domain so if I'm
dealing with a complex business domain
I might have a bunch of very simple kind
of domain models just to show the major
two main elements entities deployment
diagrams infrastructure diagrams the
runtime behavioral stuff that we've
already talked about and there are
probably a couple others as well which
is getting about but yeah they you know
for me the c4 stuff is about describing
the static structure and then okay are
there similar approaches to see for
anything that inspired you
no not really um this is pretty much the
way that I've always thought about and
therefore described software system so
it's so this is where you come from
now just the way that I've worked since
since doing this I've been pointed to a
couple of other things which have some
similarities so there's something called
sysml
heard of system but they were look into
it yeah so I looked into it briefly and
against one of those things that I don't
see people using an anger I've come
across maybe half a dozen other particle
here to Houston and suddenly pointed me
to arc 42 you've heard about 42 I've
heard of it and I actually used it right
because it's a Germans withdrawing guys
yes yeah so yeah when I saw the c-4 I
was like ah that looks kind of according
to its similarities yeah and I think
there's an English version of the of the
arc 42 documentation said what house
tonight and am i right in saying that it
has different levels like level zero
little what novel to see I think some
concepts are similar this is not
something like looked into heavily okay
it's on my to-do list Natalie at the
interstate okay okay then the rev up how
do we actually effective sketches look
like
affective sketches so effects of
scriptures are really simple number one
make sure that you and the team
understands a common way of thinking and
what I mean what I mean by that is make
sure you agree on the set of
abstractions so whether that's my C form
or Menino systems contains components
classes or something else it doesn't
really matter but make sure you have a
way to describe and think about software
systems and you have consistent
vocabulary once you've done that to
understand how you you draw a diagram
showing each of those things separately
and that's what the c4 model does and in
terms of the sketching you know it's
really simple just be conscious about
that notation so if you're using
different shapes different colors make
sure we have a little key legend to the
order to explain what that stuff means
how a title on diagrams don't leave
arrows are annotated makes your arrows
go in one way only and it's all of that
stuff so it's so just try to create as
simple a notation as possible and if you
if you do need to highlight different
elements make sure it's explained in the
key this is basically what maps do if we
go get two maps of Amsterdam they'll
both show the same things the same
abstractions but they might use
different colors and notations music
exactly that's important okay
easiest way to do this is show something
else outside of your team diagram and
they say if they say what's that mean
then you know this is more stuck in each
other inaudible maps show highlights and
right you probably also want to show
only the eyelids yeah okay okay
software architecture Perez's code why I
said versus code because historically
this is you know software architecture
and software development although
they're really two sides of the same
coin they've always been competing
forces and you can see this with you
know the ivory tower architects on one
side and the software developers on the
other and the world's never match and
I'll give you a really simple example
I've often seen teams with nice big
architecture diagrams on their wall and
they have all these kind of
brand terms and very fluffy conceptual
boxes can you finds those boxes in the
code alright so if there's a bunch of
components listed how easy is it to find
those components in the code base and
the answer is actually not all laughter
and that's the vs. bit that's the
conflict arrow that's the core of image
the diagrams well right so why not and
then and therefore how can we make it
match the diagrams and vice-versa so how
can we do it so there are lots of ways
to do it the way I do it it is again
through the c4 model so let's say we've
opened up our web app and we're listing
a bunch of components in our web app
what I want to do my code base is I want
to make sure I can explicitly find those
components George Fairbank - who wrote a
book called just enough software
architecture he calls this the model
current gap so in other words when we
have a model of our Arctic Tropper wall
and we have our code there's a gap where
these two things never meet and he says
very simply all you need to do is adopt
what he calls an architectural you have
an encoding cell so in other words when
you're coding you dropping hints that
portray your architectural intent
examples being this comes back to that
the naming convention thing so if you're
building a quote-unquote service or
component or module make sure some class
somewhere or some interface has the
words so the approach I take is called
package by component so if you if you
take a traditional enterprise Java
system there are a number of ways that
you can structure and organize your code
base one is the kind of package by layer
approach so you have a web layer and you
have a business layer and you have a
data layer and in the web lab or
controllers and the business layer
you've got services and then the data
leave but repositories and Tector access
objects there's a whole reason why
perhaps we shouldn't do that but that's
horizontal layering you've got vertical
aiming which is packaged by feature so
you kind of relate the controller's the
services and the data access object and
you align those to some functional group
if you just add like a bang
concept whatever is and I use a hybrid
approach so I keep my web stuff separate
because that's presentation tier and
it's going to potentially have a
different volatilities thruster codebase
and I structure my codebase in terms of
components so yeah basically you do
vertical slices of the feature and but
but the vertical slice has no it's just
a logical view on it so if there is
anything like a web front-end it's just
an adapter on top of it right yeah yeah
so it's easy so you can think of the the
web stuff has been a layer on top of a
bunch of components and then from your
from your web controller perspective for
example essentially you just wire in all
the commands they need so mainly have a
customer component and an order
component and an audit component and all
of those things will be separate for
things in my code base and what I do is
I've bundled up all of the classes so
the services the business object the
data access object into a single in this
case java package i make the interface
public and i make all of the
implementation details package protected
but that means also i have to work very
incremental and always go back to the
model because i can't imagine I do my
models and then I start coding and then
it's like hmm
not as I thought and then I have to go
back and that's the models to the codes
and that's how it works
no not so much so I but by morning do
you mean like the the view models that
you use on the front end for example I
don't know what I mean there's the for
instance of component view right so I
want to see my my biological model in
the code you know I make my MOT logical
model yeah and then I start calling and
then of course it's going to be very
different different things different and
then I have to go back and adjust my
models so by marching in the diagram the
diagram yeah yeah
so so that's that's the other reason why
I'm trying to automatically scrape these
components out the code weights because
then you just start coding and you run
you unbuttoning get reproached the model
for you the diagram model so yes I take
this package by component approach and
probably interface everything else is
patched protected but and that's you
know all of the business logic and all
of the data access watch it
so essentially what you've got is a
component with layers inside it rather
than structuring your codebase by a
layer front and and this is this is kind
of nice because it it brings back
modularity to your world so you know
everything to do with the customer
Poland sits in the single Java package
some popular technologies destroyed its
virulence by introducing the control
yeah and of course in Java if you do the
package by layer thing in order for the
layers above to talk to layers
underneath you need stuff public and as
soon as you start having lots of public
classes in your code base guess what
happens people find them and call them
so what this package by component thing
does is it uses the Java access
modifiers properly I'm going to use air
quotes around properly so that if if
somebody wants access to my customer
information because the data access
object is package protected they can't
get it so they're forced to go through
the public component face and exactly
layer printing more common than it
should be
yes okay so we said when I'm sketching
on the whiteboard
I should I shouldn't save the images
somewhere in the document I rather take
the images
essays in the codes and then I'd check
it in is that my my documentation so I
if I'm running a workshop like in like a
very early design workshop and coming up
with sketches then I will also take some
photos and to keep those now either
my email or sticking on a wiki or share
from server whatever but it's really one
I want to start formalizing those
diagrams either for documentation or for
sharing with teams are located close by
then that's when I start to you know put
them into Visio or now operators are
after tomorrow with code now and you
know if you do use the structure eyes of
stuff and create software technologies
version of all so you can check the
model in the long side of your codebase
and then as part of your build process
you can run it extracting concepts check
back in again and you can see smaller
changes because I images it's probably
hard to see yeah yeah especially if
you're trying to run a diff tool against
two it doesn't work very well does it no
okay so we go
I could Bob he said once at the YAC
picture should scream at me when I look
at the code and so you want to see the
architecture in the code and you don't
want to see frameworks like spring or no
so so I actually agree with in there so
that you know the architecture and also
when you're offline copies it should
scream something about the domain that
you're working in and of course that's
what package by layer does not give you
because you see web stuff that business
stuff then data access stuff sometimes
you know you see framework lengths
leaking and package by component package
by feature both give you a different
perspective codebase now coming back to
diagrams again when you look at the
container and component diagrams
although they do show tech choices the
tech choices are only only a small part
of the diagram you could you can scrub
off all the tech choices and you still
have the name and and crucially the set
responsible
is that each container or component it
does and again that's about screaming
much more about the business domain than
just having a bunch of tackle boxes
talking to them so yeah I'm also a big
fan of diagrams and coach screaming
simply lengthy to mania myself right so
so so screaming about the domain in
which okay okay yeah you don't want to
see controller right yeah but of course
I do want to be able to find the
technology choices of what when I when I
need to so if something is using spring
mahogany I do want to be able to find
that there's no - Tom okay you roll a
whole chapter in your book on software
architecture documentation I don't know
anybody who likes it so what what why
should we do it all because although we
can focus on writing clean code and the
temple code and readable code and we can
refactor our methods so they fit on page
and you know the methods fit in our head
or not and all that sort of stuff and we
can say that the tests documents some
degree of what the code does for me the
code doesn't tell the whole story that's
the fundamental point here the code
tells you how it works it doesn't tell
you why it works in that way it doesn't
tell you the rationale for crafting a
design in a certain like so the doc the
documentation is not only about the
diagram it's also about decisions yeah
yeah so it's decisions it's rationale
it's you know what were the architecture
drivers that led us to this design you
know particularly list of non-functional
it is how do you maintain it support it
operator
how many dealing with security it's all
of that stuff we used into a lightweight
software guide but I call it it's good
it's kind of like and and I can't take
credit for this but some need described
it as a as the Haynes manual 3 for your
for your software so it there's a series
of books I think it's in the UK called
that hands manual and basically it tells
you how to take your car apart it's the
same sort of thing so it's so this guide
book tells you not how to set your
software apart but how your software
works and you know the right
I went into it it's it took into our
travel guidebook know if you've got a
holiday somewhere you don't want to know
everything there is to know about the
country of visiting though you want to
know select things you want to know the
important highlights the salient points
of interests that's really what this
lightweight adaptations all about ok so
I basically don't create a large
software architecture document with
everything just the things everybody
should understand the major technology
decisions maybe right it's the
Schneiderman's matter again so overview
first zoom and filter and then
details-on-demand we can get from the
code so one of the things I find people
do is they write lots of really low
level implementation details as
documentation if you think about from
that four seconds who's the audience
it's us as developers but we know where
to get that if we know where to look so
it's a really it's a lightweight
documentation is a it's a supplementary
piece of documentation to help you
navigate the codebase okay ideally
something you're reading I want two
hours but so ideally something you can
read them while Hausman okay just to get
my Sophie and then you dive into the
code and you mentioned MEPs and science
and history culture and practical
information below what is the site then
a site so what I mean by site is a point
of interest so you know you come to
understand there are a few places you
should go visit and so the rest of the
street you can did not if you look at so
let's take a web application and let's
say that the web application has 200
different pages that a user can interact
with do you want to document all those
200 pages and the answer's no but what
you do want to document is the points of
interest the silencer and for me that's
really the core repeating patterns that
we see over and over again so maybe
those 200 pages there are four five six
interesting patterns repeated a number
of times it's let's document patterns
forget the rest
it's the pet in soccer architecture
terms and other term pick
so texture is repeating way of doing
certain things is that also other side
certain I'm thinking more principles
here so you know the the underlying
architectural principles and styles so
so things like you know usage of web
every see may be uses usage where you've
got some asynchronous data coming back
to browser that's an interesting Pataca
okay so it's really types of ways of
doing things I'm not sure whether that's
the same as the text just think okay
yeah the picture is for instance as I
learn it or we offer a web service and
then there is always one way of doing
certain type of service or there was
right if you understand one web service
you understand the principle of every
website style once is same thing yeah
yeah yeah okay which of course means you
have to agree on standards right which
of course you should do you should you
should try and agree some let's call it
principles rather the standards but some
principles and before you start writing
massive amounts of code on was you'll
get inconsistency we've all been there
done that history and culture what's
what's history of culture history and
culture is really how did we get to
where we are so you know I'm thinking
about things like what are the key
architectural drivers the key
requirements the key quality attributes
the key constraints at the time many
organizations so you must use this
version of WebSphere and this version of
Java and then three years later somebody
comes in says why are you idiots using
this version it's out of date and then
you say well that's part of the history
and how you got it and culture is really
the development principles that we all
adopt and using the databases yeah I
know that from people asking why the
hell did you do it like this and and now
then it's like oh I have to expend it
again because they're yeah we had this
non-functional requirements in them
let's double review okay yeah they did
the example I gave you so if you ever go
to Jersey where there
there's a really nice castle which is
it's a little island by itself it's
called to Elizabeth castle and I think
it was built in the 15th or 16th or 17th
century it's really kind of an old
granite castle and if you get a visit
there you've got this kind of beautiful
stone architecture and then someone
stuck a big concrete thing on top like
it's a really really eye-opening
concrete building literary stubble right
on top of the castle and you walk around
and you think wine earth is that ugly
concrete thing on top and then you read
the history I get it and basically when
Jersey was occupied in World War 2 the
Germans came home and refortified the
existing fortifications again it's part
part of history there's a story to be
told there but it's then the decision
knock is the signal of been the same
then in culture yeah so you know if we
have to evaluate different choices then
that's what I'll keep in the decision
model so there's there's definitely some
overlap there okay maybe it's by just
about you know we evaluate in these
products and this one also suitable for
these reasons so decision log is only
about technology choices or but not
about architectural choice both so it
could be architectural choices which may
be based upon spikes or proof concept
work it could be choices made relating
to skills of the team so we chose to use
this technology because we didn't have
any other developers in new technology
why you know all of that stuff just
needs to be kept somewhere okay okay the
decision lock and all these kind of
things I'm just wondering how do I write
it maintain it and make it searchable
because the decision gets me something
I'm interested is it that big that I
have to bother or is it for me just a
couple of pages that shows as you can
possibly get it okay so a couple of
pages sounds perfect to me and you know
there's no there's nothing saying this
must be in a massive Word document you
can stick on a wiki if you want to and
you can take my guide book structure and
create one page per section on my wiki
that's why it's all searchable how do
you keep up to date just do anything
really so
if you if you have like a definition of
done for your tasks if you want user
stories whatever you had a line the
bottom says have you updated the
documentation and the diagrams does need
okay and then psych tumors were rather
than some like me sitting around at the
end of project for three months Rogers
writing documentation now let's move so
if it's disappears up then nobody
forgets it reviewed if you do okay yeah
hopefully now if it gets it met okay but
okay is there anything important I
forgot to ask is really thing important
he forgot to ask I think I what we've
discussed covers a lot of the technical
aspects so diagramming thing about such
documenting an thing there are a
lot of questions around the role of
architects you know is the ivory tower
architecture thing a good thing should
we go for something more climate of mine
my general approach is architecture
should write code probably should come
as no surprise since my websites called
coding the architecture now and for me
you know it's a very hands-on
collaborative role helping team members
coaching mentoring now something really
interesting book published recently by
Patrick quat it's called talking with
tech leads Patrick's definition of tech
mean is basically someone who's leading
the team so setting the tempo vision
answered more technical questions but
still writing code I think it's just
thirty percent of the time so what he
calls tech lead is what I call a kind of
hands-on fragment experiment okay and
that's I think the other major area so
it's just how to you know how to
effectively lead a team from an
architectural or technical perspective
but stay part of the team
well okay interesting I just thought
I've heard about the book yeah and I
thought it was more of the generality
right tonight it's I mean it's
definitely focus on tech leads and it's
a fascinating book actually there's lots
of really interesting stories from
people who you toggle and people are
much more experienced and there are some
really interesting recurring themes
time management stepping away from the
keyboard not entirely but too
and all the meetings and do all of the
other stuff and really just dealing with
people as a whole there's a whole soft
skills and there that nobody talks about
I think that's what's great about
Patrick's book soft stuff it's the hard
stuff it was a hard time yeah okay how
can the listeners find out more website
book review and training conferences all
of those things so the easiest thing is
to just Google me normally come up on
first page of Google but coding the
architecture calm is the best starting
point for with this so that's that's our
blog and there are links to the books so
if you go to a lean pub and do a search
for software architecture you'll find
the book it's called software artists
for developers there's an online
training course on parlays comm which is
everything you get in the kind of
standard to their course without all of
the interaction and workshopping and
diagramming stuff and I'm usually at
conferences all around the place so I've
got a bunch of conferences scheduled in
Europe and I'm going to the US SATs I'm
going to the O'Reilly software
architects conference in Boston and then
I'm back to the ers in people for the
Saturn conference okay so yeah lots of
lots of concerts Australia okay Thank
You Simon for being on the show I want
to mention that the feedback of the
listeners is very important to us so
please help us improving our show and if
your opinion via Twitter Google+ or
Litton this is when you are also
engineering radio thanks for listening
to se Radio an educational program
brought to you by I Triple E software
magazine for more information about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se - radio man to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on iTunes mention a message us on
Twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us a team at SES radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]
you